Santa Barbara, CA, USA

☐ +1 805 895 0976

☑ alice.lepissier@gmail.com
☑ www.alicelepissier.com
in alicelepissier
☑ alicelepissier
☑ walice
⑤ alice.lepissier

Alice Lépissier

Political economist and data scientist with experience in climate policy and international development. Specialty includes bridging research and policy interface by combining quantitative research with pragmatic policy proposals and designing intuitive tools to aid decision-making.

Education

- 2021 **PhD**, *Environmental Science and Management*, Bren School of Environmental Science and Management, University of California, Santa Barbara.
 - Awarded Bren School Recruitment Fellowship
 - o Research on tropical deforestation, illicit financial flows, and climate change
- 2020 Master of Arts, Statistics, University of California, Santa Barbara.
 - Data Science specialization
 - o GPA: 4.0
- 2011 Master of Science, Economic History, London School of Economics.
 - Awarded with Merit
 - Dissertation: "Adaptation strategies and market responses to deal with uncertainty in rain-fed agriculture in Sub-Saharan Africa"
- 2010 Master of Science, Economics and Public Policy, Sciences Po Paris jointly with École Polytechnique.
 - o Quantitative economics program to elaborate and evaluate public policies in a wide range of contexts
 - o Events director for student organization on development in Sub-Saharan Africa · Managed 15 society members
- 2009 Bachelor of Arts, European Social and Political Studies, University College London.
 - Awarded with First Class Honors
 - o 2006-2007 Sessional Prize awarded for academic merit
 - Year abroad at the Universidad Complutense de Madrid
- 2005 French Baccalaureate, International Option, Lycée International de Saint Germain en Laye, France.
 - o Awarded with honors 'Mention Très bien' (highest possible) · top 3% of test takers · Economics track

Experience

2015-present **Consultant**, *Various organisations*.

- o Development of open data tool for the Tax Justice Network quantifying risk exposure to illicit financial flows
- Quantitative modeling of foreign direct investment and illicit financial flows for the United Nations Economic Commission for Africa
- Scoping report for the Global Commission on Business and Sustainable Development on how the private sector can contribute to the Sustainable Development Goals
- Quantitative analysis and creation of user-friendly replication tool for the Tax Justice Network on how much capital
 is held offshore
- 2014–2015 Research Associate, Center for Global Development, London.
 - o Lead modeler of tool SkyShares.org which allows policy-makers to compute economic costs of a climate deal
 - o Conceptualized and developed website with intuitive user interface for decision-makers
 - Quantitative and qualitative research: economic modeling, drafting policy papers and blog posts
 - o Policy outreach and engagement on climate agreements, climate finance, and illicit financial flows
- 2012–2014 Research Assistant, Center for Global Development, London.

Evidence driven research on illicit financial flows and climate change to develop practical policy proposals.

Summer 2009 **Consultant**, *LaquaR Consultants CC*, Cape Town.

Research for report on Namibian sea-level rise for the Namibian Ministry of Environment and Tourism.

Summer 2009 Research, ICLEI Africa Secretariat, Cape Town.

Research on climate change adaptation for the city of Cape Town.

2007 & 2006 Summer Internships, BRED Banque Privée, Paris, Private Wealth Management division.

Teaching

- Spring 2019 POLS 15 Introduction to Research Methods, Department of Political Science, Teaching assistant.
- Spring 2018 **ESM 269/ED 218 Survey Design and Environmental Public Opinion**, *Cross-listed Bren School and Department of Education*, Teaching assistant.

Average ESCI score (1 = best, 5 = worst): 1.14

- Spring 2017 **ESM 210 Business and the Environment**, *Bren School of Environmental Science and Management*, Grader.
 - Fall 2017 **POLS 15 Introduction to Research Methods**, *Department of Political Science*, Teaching assistant. Average ESCI score (1 = best, 5 = worst): 1.19

Professional courses

Feb 2014 Practical General Equilibrium Modeling with GAMS

EcoMod, Boston, MA

June 2013 SQL Data Management

Impartica IT Training, Leeds, UK

June 2013 Panel Data Analysis using Stata

Timberlake, London, UK

Computing

Methods econometrics \cdot machine learning \cdot Integrated Assessment Modeling \cdot Computable General Equilibrium modeling \cdot website development \cdot user experience design \cdot database management

 $Languages \quad R \cdot Stata/Mata \cdot Visual \ Basic \cdot JavaScript \cdot T_{E}X$

main working languages

Python · SQL · MATLAB · HTML

capable

Selected SkyShares (JavaScript) · Bézier spline interpolation ($Visual\ Basic$) · Illicit financial flows (Stata) · Genetic repositories algorithm (R)

Languages

Fluent French (native) · Spanish · English

Conversational Italian

Presentations

- 2019 o "Assessing the causal impact of UK climate policy using synthetic controls: an impact analysis of the 2001 Climate Change Programme", 5th Annual Conference on Environmental Politics and Governance, University of California, Santa Barbara, USA
 - "Mapping developing countries' exposure to illicit financial flows: a new data-set of risk measures",
 Development Studies Association Annual Conference 2019, The Open University, UK
 - "The environmental effectiveness of UK climate reforms: An impact analysis of the 2001 Climate Change Programme", Duck Family Graduate Workshop on Environmental Politics and Governance, *University of Washington*, USA
 - "Assessing the Causal Impact of Carbon Pricing Using Synthetic Control Methods: An Impact Analysis of the UK's Climate Change Programme", Bren PhD Symposium, *University of California, Santa Barbara*, USA
 - o "Trade mis-invoicing estimates in Africa", Inception Meeting on Preventing Trade Mis-invoicing in Selected African Countries, *UN Economic Commission for Africa*, Ethiopia

- 2018 o Expert meeting on statistical methodologies for measuring illicit financial flows, Sustainable Development Goal 16.4.1, *UN Conference on Trade and Development*, Switzerland
- 2015 o "Ice and Climate Science Question Time with the Experts", University of Newcastle, UK
 - o "Economics of climate change: Extension or Reinvention?", Warwick Climate Forum, University of Warwick, UK
- 2014 o "How can financial markets help us tackle climate change?", University of Warwick, UK
 - o "Stakeholder perspectives on climate change adaptation", JPI Climate, Euro-Mediterranean Center on Climate Change, Italy
- 2013 o "Exposure to illicit flows in Africa", Technical Committee of the High Level Panel on Illicit Financial Flows from Africa, UN Economic Commission for Africa, Ethiopia
 - "An illicit flows target for post-2015", Conference on Illicit Financial Flows, Academics Stand Against Poverty, UK
- 2010 o Interview with Youssou N'Dour about African development, *Sciences Po Paris*, France Event filmed for Senegalese television · Organized the event & negotiated free concert · 200 attended

Publications

August 2019 **Tax Justice Network report**, *Vulnerability and Exposure to Illicit Financial Flows in Africa*.

AUTHORS: C. Abugre, A. Cobham, R. Etter-Phoya, A. Lépissier, M. Meinzer, N. Monkam and A. Mosioma

Available here

December Technical note, "Chapter 5: Cheaper, Cooler, Faster: Reducing Tropical Deforestation for a More Cost-

2016 Effective Global Response to Climate Change" In Why Forests? Why Now? The Science, Economics, and Politics of Tropical Forests and Climate Change, Frances Seymour and Jonah Busch. Brookings Institution Press, Washington, DC.

AUTHORS: J. Busch, J. Engelmann and A. Lépissier

Available here

September **CGD Policy Paper series**, *SkyShares: Modelling the Economic Implications of a Future Global Emissions* 2015 *Budget*, Policy Paper 067.

AUTHORS: O. Barder, A. Evans and A. Lépissier

Available here

September **Technical paper**, *Modelling SkyShares: Technical background*.

2015 AUTHORS: A. Lépissier, O. Barder and A. Evans

Available here

June 2015 **UNA-UK report**, "A global emissions budget." In *Climate 2020 - Facing the Future*, Report by the United Nations Association - UK.

AUTHORS: O. Barder, A. Lépissier and A. Evans

Available here

January 2015 **Contributed chapters**, *Track it! Stop it! Get it! Report of the High Level Panel on Illicit Financial Flows from Africa*, Commissioned by the AU/ECA Conference of Ministers of Finance, Planning and Economic Development.

AUTHORS: African Union and United Nations Economic Commission for Africa

Available here

August 2013 **Journal of International Development**, Europe Beyond Aid: Assessing European countries' individual and collective commitment to development, Vol. 25, Issue 6.

AUTHORS: O. Barder, J. Clark, A. Lépissier, L. Reynolds and D. Roodman.

Available here

December **CGD Working Paper series**, Europe Beyond Aid: Assessing Europe's commitment to development, 2012 Working Paper 313.

AUTHORS: O. Barder, J. Clark, A. Lépissier, L. Reynolds and D. Roodman.

Available here

Other writing and referee activity

Blogging Various posts on *Views from the Center for Global Development*, including "Setting a Price on Carbon Immediately Is Necessary to Avoid Dangerous Climate Change" and "A Global Carbon Tax or Cap-and-Trade? Part 1: The Economic Arguments".

Op-ed "Global goals can deliver on 2°C and new development finance - here's how", The Guardian, 9/24/15.

Referee Journal of Environment and Development

Fellowships and grants

- 2017 Energy and Climate Graduate Fellow of the Scholars Strategy Network
- 2016 Bren School of Environmental Science and Management Recruitment Fellowship

for 3 years

- 2016 International Doctoral Recruitment Fellowship, University of California Santa Barbara
- 2016 "The economic prize for business of achieving the Sustainable Development Goals", Business and Sustainable Development Commission, research grant number BSDC-02
- "The Price of Offshore, robust replication", Tax Justice Network, research grant 2016
- 2013 "The Political Economy of Illicit Financial Flows in Africa and their Impact on Africa's Development", United Nations Economic Commission for Africa, grant with Alex Cobham, \$25,000

References

Owen Barder

Precision Agriculture for Development

Matthew Potoski

Professor of Corporate Environmental Management Assistant Professor of Political Science UC Santa Barbara

Alex Cobham

CEO

Tax Justice Network

□ alex@taxjustice.net

Matto Mildenberger

UC Santa Barbara